Finding Aid for Urban League of Greater Muskegon Records 1943-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Urban League of Greater Muskegon Records 1943-1995, 1943-1992
Urban League of Greater Muskegon.
17.5 linear feet
Records of the Urban League of Greater Muskegon and its predecessor the Citizen's Recreation Association of Muskegon. Board of directors files, executive director's files, community organization department files, printed material, newspaper clippings, photographs, and miscellanea.
85469 Bd 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group (Donor No. 4198 ) has come to the library in two principal accessions, in 1964 and 1995.
The record group is open for research.
The forerunner of the organization that became the Urban League of Greater Muskegon was the Citizens' Recreation Association, Inc., which was incorporated in February 1944. Established as an interracial, non-profit community service organization, the Citizens' Recreation Association sought to address the education, recreation, and welfare needs of the then 500 African American citizens of the greater Muskegon area.
In 1949, the Citizens' Recreation Association affiliated with the National Urban League becoming the Urban League of Greater Muskegon. The organization is governed by a multi-racial board of governors; its mission is to promote, encourage, assist, and engage in activities designed to improve the social and economic conditions of African Americans and other minority group members in Muskegon County. In order to achieve this goal, the chapter conducts programs intended to strengthen the growth and development of the African American community. Additionally, it conducts in-depth research to identify the social welfare needs of individuals and families. The Greater Muskegon chapter works extensively with existing institutions, both public and private, to make them more aware and responsive to these needs. Finally, it mobilizes and organizes the community to work for the development of alternatives to systems that have been identified as inadequate.
Examples of services provided by the Urban League of Greater Muskegon include health services, such as AIDS prevention and information, high blood pressure detection and counseling, and sickle cell anemia detection; youth employment training programs, including vocational exploration, part-time jobs that provide training and social skills that are needed in the workplace; adult employment services and information referrals, for those seeking services not offered by the Urban League; and other community and educational services.
The records of the Urban League of Greater Muskegon have come to the library in two principal accessions, in 1964 and 1995. Included are correspondence, minutes, reports, printed materials, and newspaper clippings documenting the work of the organization. The record group has been divided into the following series:
History/Background Information
Board of Directors
Organizational
Executive Director
Topical File
Community Organization Department
Urban League Guild of Greater Muskegon
Printed Material
Newspaper Clippings
Health Topical File
Programs
Related Organizations
Photographs
Subjects:
African Americans--Michigan--Muskegon.; Civil rights--Michigan--Muskegon.; Muskegon (Mich.); National Urban League.; Social service--Michigan--Muskegon--Societies, etc.; Urban League of Greater Muskegon.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans--Michigan--Muskegon--Health and welfare.; African Americans--Michigan--Muskegon--Organizations.; African Americans--Michigan--Muskegon--Social life and customs.; Celebrations.; Chansonettes.; Children.; Clothing and dress.; Community service.; Music ensembles.; Musical revues and comedies.; Poliomyelitis.; Reading.; Urban League of Greater Muskegon.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- History/Background Information
  The History/Background Information series includes the League's articles of association and bylaws (1988), lists of past directors, articles of incorporation, memorabilia from the 40th anniversary of the Urban League of Greater Muskegon, and scattered issue of the chapter's different newsletters.
  - Articles of incorporation and bylaws (Box 1)
  - Historical and miscellaneous information (Box 1)
  - Newsletter: Gazet, 1948-1960, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Newsletter: Awareness and Urban News and Update, 1980-1981, 1990 (Box 1)
- Board of Directors
  Board of Directors is a series that consists of minutes and reports (1943-1962 and 1982-1983), annual reports, 1963-1990, and general administrative information (1947-1961 and 1983-1995). The annual report typically includes the following: Message from the President of the 16 member Executive Board, Executive Director's message (day to day administrator), summation and results of the year's projects, and a condensed financial report.
  - Minutes and reports
    (includes annual reports)
    - 1943-1962, 16 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes and reports 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    (formerly in binder)
  - Annual reports 1963-1990 (scattered dates), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Planning 1982, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - General undated, 1947-1961 (scattered), 5 folders (Box 1)
  - General 1983-1995, 16 folders (Box 14)
- Organizational
  Organizational is a series documenting the annual meetings of the chapter and the workings of the various area committees.
  - Annual Meetings 1950-1960, 10 folders (Box 2)
  - Community Organization Committee undated, 1951-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Education Committee 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Financial; Statements and related 1947-1992 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Relations Committee 1951-1958 (Box 2)
  - Membership campaign 1948-1961, 14 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership miscellaneous and mailings 1982-1986, 1991, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Personnel Committee undated, 1949-1961, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Public Relations Committee 1951-1955 (Box 2)
  - Roster and policy documents (Box 2)
    (formerly maintained in binder)
- Executive Director
  The Executive Director series includes correspondence (1947-1962) as well as files for individual executive directors. There are files for Jesse Carter, Stephen Pressley, Dorothy Spurlock, Donald Everette, and Gloria White Gardner. These records help to reveal the broader extent of their duties as well as their personal involvement. As with the Board of Directors, this series contains a wide array of written communication involving various individuals and organizations detailing orders, upcoming events, and general administrative business.
  - Correspondence 1947-1962, 22 folders (Box 3)
  - By name
    - Jesse Carter 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - Donald Everette 1989-1990, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Gloria White Gardner 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - Stephen Pressley 1982-1989 (scattered), 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Dorothy Spurlock 1988-1991 (Box 3)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - 1990-1991, 8 folders (Box 18)
- Topical File
  - Annual Dinners 1972, 1981, 1984-1988, 1991, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Annual Golf Classic 1993, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Annual Midnight Shows 1948-1951, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Birthday Party for Mary Gregory 1956 (Box 4)
  - Boy Scouts 1959-1961 (Box 4)
  - Ebony Fashion Fair 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Equal Opportunity Day 1956-1958 (Box 4)
  - Fortieth Anniversary Yearbook 1950 (Box 4)
  - German Visitors 1954 (Box 4)
  - Goodwill Conferences 1949-1951 (Box 4)
  - Greater Muskegon FEPC Advisory Council 1957-1958, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Indoor International Exposition 1958 (Box 4)
  - Lillian Smith Lecture 1952 (Box 4)
  - Membership Meetings 1955-1960 (Box 4)
  - Milwaukee Regional Conference 1951 (Box 4)
  - Ministers' Luncheon 1954 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous undated, 1945-1962, 10 folders (Box 4)
  - Muskegon County Community Council undated, 1948-1952, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - National Negro Health Week 1947-1951, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - National Urban League Board Convention 1955, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - National Urban League Conference 1949-1960, 21 folders (Box 5)
  - National Urban League Manual 1958 (Box 5)
  - National Urban League memoranda
    - Undated 1949-1950, 7 folders (Box 5)
    - 1951-1959, 23 folders (Box 6)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - Organizations for Fundraising 1980s (Box 7)
  - Pension Plan (Box 7)
  - Personnel
    - Community Organization Secretary 1952-1960 (scattered), 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Barbara Fowler 1950-1955 (Box 7)
    - Doris Gallimore 1948-1952 (Box 7)
    - Mary Gregory 1954-1960 (Box 7)
  - Press releases undated, 1948-1961, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Program Workshop 1952 (Box 7)
  - Public Meeting on Law Enforcement 1950 (Box 7)
  - Radio Scripts undated, 1950, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Social Agency Workers of Muskegon 1960 (Box 7)
  - Speeches undated (Box 7)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes 1951-1958, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Theater Project 1956-1957 (Box 7)
  - West-Central Michigan Regional Social Welfare Conference 1955 (Box 7)
- Community Organizational Department
  Community Organization Department (1947-1960) consists of reports, correspondence, and a topical file documenting various organizations and activities. This topical file also includes personnel information, press releases, and speeches.
  - Reports 1948-1956, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence 1948-1960, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Topical File
    - Adult Education undated, 1948-1957, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Bill Layton Bon Voyage Party 1954 (Box 7)
    - Church Activities undated, 1954-1959 (Box 7)
    - Clean-Up Campaign 1953 (Box 7)
    - Clubs and Organizations 1947-1958 (Box 7)
    - Community Organizations Council of the National Urban League 1950-1952 (Box 7)
    - Coordinating Committee on Race Relations undated, 1950-1951 (Box 7)
    - East Park Area Council 1957-1961, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Geriatrics Council of Greater Muskegon undated, 1952-1961, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Grossman's Department Store 1950 (Box 8)
    - Health Institute 1953 (Box 8)
    - High School Graduation Parties 1949-1952 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Committee on Civil Rights 1948-1959 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous undated, 1948-1963, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Muskegon Civic League undated, 1951-1961, 9 folders (Box 8)
    - Neighborhood Units Council undated, 1954-1961, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - Pemberton Convalescent Home 1949-1952 (Box 8)
    - Program and Party Ideas undated, 1951-1956, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Safety undated, 1954-1957, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Socialized Medicine 1948-1950 (Box 8)
    - Tenants Council of Fairview Homes undated, 1949-1951, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Township Neighbors (Russell Road Area) undated, 1951-1961, 5 folders (Box 9)
    - United Church Women 1957-1959 (Box 9)
    - United League of Emerson Highlands undated, 1949-1959, 10 folders (Box 9)
    - Webster-Muskegon Avenue Neighborhood Unit undated, 1957-1961, 4 folders (Box 9)
- Urban League Guild of Greater Muskegon
  The Urban League Guild of Greater Muskegon (1949-1961) includes minutes and general information.
  - Minutes 1949-1960, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - General undated, 1947-1954, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - General 1955-1961, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    (material formerly in binder)
- Printed Material
  The Printed Material (1949-1961 and 1977-1995) series contains Urban League related materials from the national office and several affiliates.
  - National Urban League undated, 1949-1961, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Urban League Affiliates (arranged alphabetically)
    - Akron-Chicago, 11 folders (Box 10)
    - Chicago-Milwaukee, 30 folders (Box 11)
    - Minneapolis-Winston-Salem, 33 folders (Box 12)
  - Michigan undated, 1941-1962, 9 folders (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous undated, 1944-1961, 1980s, 20 folders (Box 13)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Undated 1949-1962, 19 folders (Box 13)
  - 1970s (Box 15)
  - 1980-1990s (Box 15)
- Health Topical File
  Health Topical File (1976-1993) contains extensive information dealing with AIDS, including a task force, and the Urban League of Greater Muskegon's Community Hypertension Intervention Program. Other health issues include but, are not limited to, drug education, teenage pregnancy, Wellness, the Mobile Health Fair, and Sickle Cell Anemia detection. This series also documents many of the tasks of Alecia Spigner, who was the League's Health Services Manager from 1985 to 1990. The series concludes with a comprehensive study of home health care by the West Michigan Health Systems Agency.
  - AIDS Task Force 1988-1989 (Box 15)
  - AIDS Information 1983-1993, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Coalition for Diabetes Education and Minority Health 1990-1991 (Box 15)
  - Community Health Heart Program 1992 (Box 15)
  - Community Hypertension Identification Program
    - General 1980-1992, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Budget 1981-1983, 1985-1990, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Screenings 1986-1991 (Box 15)
  - Drug Education 1980s (Box 15)
  - Mobile Health Fair Presbyterian 1988-1989 (Box 15)
  - Sickle Cell Anemia Prevention Program 1988-1991 (Box 15)
  - Alecia Spigner Health Services Memoranda 1985-1990 (Box 15)
  - Teenage Pregnancy 1985, 1995 (Box 15)
  - Wellness 1991 (Box 15)
  - West Michigan Health Systems 1976 (Box 15)
- Programs
  Programs (1980-1993; .5 linear feet) is a series that documents activities that the Urban League of Greater Muskegon has fostered, such as the voter registration drive in 1988.
  - Affirmative Action Report 1990 (Box 16)
  - Education 1989-1992 (Box 16)
  - Educational Essay Contest 1992 (Box 16)
  - Historic Black Colleges and Universities Tour 1991-1992 (Box 16)
  - Housing 1988-1992 (Box 16)
  - Job Training 1985, 1989, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Legislative Initiative Information 1988 (Box 16)
  - Minority Supplier of the Year 1986 (Box 16)
  - Muskegon County Minority Needs Assessment 1984, 1986-1987, 1991, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Performance Evaluations 1981 (Box 16)
  - Program Service Reports 1985-1988 (Box 16)
  - Racial Attitudes Survey Analysis 1986 (Box 16)
  - Scholarships 1988 (Box 16)
  - Voter Registration 1988 (Box 16)
  - Youth Programs 1987, 1990-1993 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous programs and projects (Box 16)
    (documents formerly maintained in binder)
- Related Organizations
  Related Organizations (1977-1993) detail many of the organizations with which the Urban League of Greater Muskegon has had working relationships. Some of these organizations were used for referral, some aided the Urban League, and some were aided by the Urban League.
  - Ad Hoc Committee of Concerned Citizens 1991-1992 (Box 16)
  - African-American Celebration 1992 (Box 16)
  - Black Women's Political Caucus 1990 (Box 16)
  - City of Muskegon Affirmative Action Plan 1992 (Box 16)
  - Detroit Urban League 1990 (Box 16)
  - Flint Urban League 1987 (Box 16)
  - Grand Rapids Urban League 1987-1988 (Box 16)
  - Greater Muskegon Business Success Program 1989 (Box 16)
  - Harbor Lights of the City Rescue Mission 1992-1993 (Box 16)
  - Kool Achiever Awards 1988 (Box 16)
  - Love of Muskegon County (newsletter) 1991-1992 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Council of Urban Leagues 1989 (Box 16)
  - Michigan Area Planned Parenthood 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Muskegon County 1988-1994 (Box 17)
  - Muskegon County Assembly for Senior Programs 1985 (Box 17)
  - Muskegon County Cooperative Churches 1993 (Box 17)
  - Muskegon Economic Growth Alliances 1989, 1992 (Box 17)
  - Muskegon-Oceana Area Economic Development Efforts 1989 (Box 17)
  - Muskegon-Oceana Community Action Against Poverty 1989-1990, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Muskegon Skill Training Center 1983-1986 (Box 17)
  - Muskegon 2000 Plans 1991 (Box 17)
  - National Urban League 1987, 1989, 1993, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - National Urban League Analysis of Median Housing 1991 (Box 17)
  - National Urban League Correspondence 1985 (Box 17)
  - National Urban League Developing Family-Based Services 1988 (Box 17)
  - National Urban League Minutes of the Delegate Assembly 1984 (Box 17)
  - National Urban League National Conference 1988 (Box 17)
  - National Urban League News 1988-1989 (Box 17)
  - Nelson Neighborhood Newsletter 1992-1993 (Box 17)
  - Planned Parenthood Centers of Western Michigan 1991 (Box 17)
  - Pontiac Urban League Proposal for Religious Support 1988 (Box 17)
  - Public Schools of Greater Muskegon 1987, 1989 (Box 17)
  - Salvation Army Advisory Board 1990 (Box 17)
  - United Way Allocation and Review Long-Range Planning 1982-1983 (Box 17)
  - United Way 1983-1991 (Box 17)
  - United Way at Work (newsletter) 1992-1993 (Box 17)
  - United Way Mid-year Review 1988 (Box 17)
  - United Way of Muskegon Budget 1983-1985 (Box 17)
  - Urban League Guild 1977, 1981-1985, 1987-1991, 1993, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Women of Color Reaching Out Task Force 1991 (Box 17)
- Photographs
  - Group portraits and snapshots of Urban League leaders, volunteers, and of the music ensemble, the Chansonettes; and snapshots of community service activities and special events. (Box 17)